Guide to the Robert Provo Norris Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Robert Provo Norris Collection
1846-1854
MSS 11
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
2
1 box
The collection comprises personal diaries, watercolors, and drawings by Robert Provo Norris, most of which were created while he was a soldier stationed on the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa during the Frontier ("Kaffir") Wars of the 1840s and 1850s.
Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
Hall, Morris, Captain
Mansergh, John Craven
Michell, John, Sir, 1781-1866
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired 1995, Paul Mellon Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series: I. Diaries; II. Correspondence and Writings; III. Sketchbook; IV. Watercolors and Drawings.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises personal diaries, watercolors, and drawings by Robert Provo Norris, most of which were created while he was a soldier stationed on the Cape of Good Hope in South Africa during the Frontier ("Kaffir") Wars of the 1840s and 1850s. It also includes letters written by other correspondents and miscellaneous manuscripts about his life and death. The bulk of the collection represents the years 1846-1851.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Provo Norris was born ca. 1825 at Broome in Norfolk, England, the eldest son of Reverend D.G. (Dennis George) Norris, a Church of England parson who was Vicar of St. Edmund Church, Kessingland, Suffolk for 35 years. Robert was the first of eight children born to Reverend Norris and his wife, Mary Pellew (born ca. 1800 in Halifax, Nova Scotia). Only three of the Norris children would survive childhood and live past the age of twenty-five. An illness seems to have swept the Norris household in 1844, for Mary Pellew and three of her children--Henry (1828-1844), Ellen (1840-1844),and Elizabeth (b/d 1844)--all died in this year. Reverend Norris lived on until 1865. Surviving daughters Mary (1830-1906), Christiana (1831-1895) and Rose Gernton (b. 1833, married 1863) remained in the Suffolk area for the rest of their lives.
On 9 June 1846, Norris joined the 6th Regiment in Kessingland and was stationed there for approximately two months. By 30 July 1846, he had left Kessingland and travelled to Cork, Ireland, where he remained for over one month. In early September 1846, Norris and the rest of his regiment were sent to the Cape of Good Hope. During the Napoleonic Wars, Britain took possession of the Cape of Good Hope, which was previously a Dutch colony. The Cape area was an ideal resting point for European traders en route to India. However, the original Dutch colonists in the area, many of whom were farmers, became engaged in the wars between different aboriginal African tribes, including the Xhosa. Britain became involved in the wars primarily for political reasons and to protect British trade interests. As early as 1795, British troops were sent to the Cape of Good Hope in order to keep the peace. Until 1895, the British were engaged in many frontier wars in South Africa, including but not limited to the Seventh Frontier War or the War of the Axe (1846-1847), the Xhosa/"Kaffir" Wars (1850-1853 and 1877-1878), and the Anglo-Zulu War (1879).
Although he spent over five years in South Africa, Norris was not involved in all of the Cape's numerous frontier wars. When sent to South Africa in 1846, he was first stationed at Fort Peddie, a camp situated between the Fish and Keiskamma Rivers, approximately 20 miles from the Indian Ocean. Norris and other members of the 6th Regiment were subsequently sent to Cape Town, thereby avoiding the skirmishes of the War of the Axe from 1846 to 1847. In addition, Norris spent some time at Fort Cox and approximately seven months at Fort White, where, in 1848, he was promoted to Lieutenant in the 6th Regiment.
While in Cape Town, however, Norris prepared for the forthcoming military campaigns and enjoyed weekly socializing with fellow soldiers and other British citizens living on the Cape of Good Hope. He also occupied his time by concentrating on his artwork, making watercolors and drawings of local scenes and people. Norris' diaries and art reflect his observations of life in South Africa, and his writings trace the development of a friendship and romantic relationship with a young woman named Annie de Smidt. Annie was a member of the well-established de Smidt family, of Dutch origin, who had settled in Cape Town in the early years of the nineteenth century. On May 9, 1850, just before Norris was to be thrown into battle on the eastern frontier, he wrote the following passage regarding his nearly two-year relationship with Annie: "Spent naturally a very pleasant evening, but the more I know the more difficult will it be to leave her. Such is life. We no sooner know and make friends than we are doomed to part" (Diary 1). In June, 1850, Norris' regiment was moved to the eastern frontier and involved in skirmishes during the early days of the Xhosa ("Kaffir") War.
In October 1851, members of the South African Xhosa people, then known to Britons as "Kaffirs," were gathering in great numbers near the Amatola Mountains and the town of Waterkloof, close to the Kroomie Mountains. Norris's 6th Regiment, consisting of approximately 611 soldiers and under the command of Lieutenant Colonel John Michell, was ordered to march toward the Kroomie Mountains and attack the stronghold of the Xhosa chief, Maqomo. During the early morning of October 14, 1851, while pursuing the Xhosa into the depths of the Kroomie mountain range, Norris was shot trough the abdomen as he lead his men into battle near the edge of a deep ravine; he died in his sleep later that same day. His body was taken to a nearby military post and buried by a clergyman of the English Church, Reverend J. Wilson.
There are two memorial tablets erected in memory of Norris, both of which are at St. Edmund Church, Kessingland, Suffolk. The first seems likely to have been installed by his family; it notes that he died at just 25 years of age, while leading his men in battle. The inscription on a second plaque declares it to have been "erected as a mark of esteem by his brother officers."
Bibliography
Brinton, Wilfred. History of the British Regiments in South Africa, 1795-1895. Cape Town: University of Cape Town, 1977.
Bull, Marjorie. Abraham de Smidt 1829-1908: Artist and Surveyor-General of the Cape Colony. Cape Town: Printpak, 1981.
Godlonton, Robert. A Narrative of the Kaffir War. Cape Town: C. Struik, 1962.
King, William Ross. Campaigning in Kaffirland, or, Scenes and adventures in the Kaffir war of 1851-2. London: Saunders and Otley, 1853.
Le Cordeur, Basil. The War of the Axe, 1847. Johannesburg: Brenthurst, 1981.
Lister, Georgina. Reminiscences. Johannesburg: Africana Museum/Cape Times Limited, 1960.
Robert Provo Norris Memorial Tablets, St. Edmund Church, Kessingland, Suffolk.
Suckling, Alfred. The History and Antiquities of the County of Suffolk. London: John Weale, 1846.
Wellesley, Edward. Letters of a Victorian Army Officer, Edward Wellesley. Stroud: Alan Sutton Publishing for the Army Records Society, 1995.
British -- South Africa -- History -- 19th century; Memorials; Xhosa (African people); Xhosa (African people) -- Colonization -- South Africa -- Cape of Good Hope; Cape of Good Hope (South Africa) -- Description and travel; Cape of Good Hope (South Africa) -- History -- 1795-1872; Great Britain -- Colonies -- Africa -- History -- 19th century; South Africa -- Description and travel; South Africa -- History -- Frontier Wars, 1811-1878; Diaries; Graphite drawings; Landscape drawings -- South Africa; Letters; Travel sketches -- South Africa; Views -- South Africa; Watercolors; De Smidt, Annie, 19th cent; Hall, Morris, Captain -- Correspondence; Mansergh, John Craven -- Correspondence; Michell, John, Sir, 1781-1866 -- Correspondence; Norris, Dennis George, b. 1798 or 9 -- Correspondence; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851 -- Diaries; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; Great Britain. Army. Royal Warwickshire Regiment; Great Britain. Army -- Military Life; South Africa. Army. Imperial Cape Mounted Riflemen
- Diaries, Series I
  - Diary, 1847 September 1-1850 May 9; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 182 pages; 19 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Holograph diary, including personal accounts of Norris' daily activities and observation of life in South Africa.
    Several pages at various intervals appear to have been torn out of the diary. It is not clear whether they contained any portion of text.
    The fly-leaf features a pen and ink drawing of a barking dog, along with Norris's name and regiment. It is dated August 22, 1846. "Cork Barracks" is listed as the location. Four graphite sketches, including one labeled "Cape Town" and another labeled, "Fort Albert from Camp," preface the diary portion, which begins in September, 1847. It tapers off in October, 1847 and then picks up January 1848. Norris resolves to write "more regularly than" before.
    Norris records daily life at Fort Peddie, including "[p]arade in fatigue dress," and receiving orders for various companies to ready themselves to proceed to "undetermined places." Norris also notes envying other companies sent to King William's Town, which he regards as "the best post on the Frontier," although he does acknowledge that such a designation is "not saying much..." He helps to drive cattle (a resource much fought over during the Frontier Wars), writes of a horse race held between various officers, and records official treks to King William's Town and back. Norris writes of interactions with some locals, such as the buying of a pipe from a "friendly Kaffir," but tense relationships also are in evidence: "Brought a Kaffir boy...with a rope round his neck intending to take him a prisoner...but let him go as he returned the knife he had stolen." Life at camp appears fairly comfortable for an officer like Norris, although the South African frontier presents many hazards (sunburn and dangerous waters on the "Line Drift," a path on which Norris and others drive cattle frequently).
    Norris writes of attending a court martial trial for theft in which the accused was found guilty and given "50 lashes & 6 months...hard labour." Norris's presence at other court martials is noted, including one for drunkeness. He also notes appearing in court to "give evidence on White- trial for the murder of Serg't Jelly."
    Once he is transferred to Cape Town, Norris records frequent drills and parades, as well as an active social life. He seems interested, to a certain degree, in his surroundings and in South African culture. He sketches landscapes occasionally and at one point visits an acquaintance, "who shewed me some Bushman's poisoned arrows with a quiver and bow; a great curiosity being very hard to get them; the arrows are about 1 1/2 feet in length made of reed with about an inch of bone in which is beautifully set a small iron barb which has the poison on it; they are certain death. The Caffirs dread the sight of a bushman particularly when they utter their boar cry [?] on an ostrich feather. The poison which they get from some root is only known to themselves." Norris is so well integrated into the colonial culture, however, that he does not comment frequently on such matters. He longs for mail from home, recording letters, newspapers, and copies of "Punch" sent to him by his family. He writes to loved ones in England frequently and notes, in 1848, having his "portrait taken in daguerreotype" to send home.
    Norris occupies some of his free time with reading, noting that Sheridan's "School for Scandal" is one of his favorite works. He also reads the work of Alexandre Dumas and Horatio Smith. Norris's journal records many dances and other assemblies at which the British and Dutch citizens of Cape Town are present. In particular, Norris grows close to a young woman named Annie de Smidt and remarks upon the occasions when he can dance with her or escort her home. Norris calls frequently on the de Smidt family. Annie was the fourth of six children of Johannes de Smidt, Esq., the Assistant Commissary General. Annie's cousin, Abraham de Smidt, Jr., became a well-known surveyor for the Colonial government and a keen landscape watercolorist.
    At the close of the journal, in May of 1850, Norris is ready to ship out on the "Hermes," and reflects on having to leave Cape Town. He seems to want to draw his relationship with Annie to a close, although he records giving her a brooch and confessing his feelings of love to her, shortly before his departure.
    Xhosa (African people); South Africa -- History -- Frontier Wars, 1811-1878; Diaries; De Smidt, Annie, 19th century; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1848 September 8-1851 October 9; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 160 pages (with many blanks); 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Holograph diary, including an alphabetical roll of British squads, personal entries and notes about Norris' debts and expenditures, some graphite sketches, and one pen and ink sketch.
    The diary's fly-leaf has pen and ink drawing of a barking dog and the inscription "R.P. Norris." It contains various types of entries, the first being an alphabetical roll of "No. 2 Squad of 'B' or Captain E. Staunton's Company, 22nd Sept. 1847." Soldiers' vital statistics (age, height, marital status, etc.) are recorded here.
    There are several pages of journal entries (in graphite and pen-and-ink), most of which record increasingly dangerous conditions near Fort White. Norris writes of multiple skirmishes involving heavy gunfire which incurred serious losses. He writes of seeing men dead on the battlefield and of the wounding of his friend "Cathy," a fellow soldier mentioned frequently in his other diary. Details of the native tribespeople's intimidating presence are found here--Norris at one points notes that "heat and fatigue compelled...[some] to drop coats and blankets which the enemy picked up and displayed to us, yelling most frightfully."
    After a particularly serious skirmish, Norris writes, "what was our horror on seeing 15 of our countrymen lying dead partially stripped, 7 with them about 4 kaffirs & 2 wagon drivers. It was indeed a painful sight and to be obliged to leave the bodies unburied." Gunfire is never far away from the men at Fort White, and it is almost constantly within earshot, according to Norris's entries. The situation seems very grim as the diary entries cease, suggesting that Norris continued to face dangerous encounters with the opposing forces on a regular basis.
    A few graphite sketches show landscapes and some small studies of various figures. At the back of the volume are pages of accounts paid and received, some of which consist of notes penned by other soldiers, stating that they have received money from Norris (presumably to pay back a debt).
    South Africa -- History -- Frontier Wars, 1811-1878; Xhosa (African people); Diaries; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851 -- Diaries
- Correspondence and Writings, Series II
  - Envelope, addressed to "Captain Lawlor, R.A., 13 Marine Parade, Lowesloff ... with Rev. Mr. D.G. Norris's kind regards and best thanks.", between 1847 and 1852?; Norris, Dennis George, b. 1798 or 9 (Box 1, Folder 3a(1))
    Includes another unsigned and undated note, in a different hand, indicating that the manuscripts originally stored in the envelope (items 3a(2-7) in the present collection) should be saved for future generations.
    Correspondence; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; Lawlor, Captain
  - Manuscript copy of a letter, dated 1851 October 15, from John Michell, Lieutenant Colonel of the 6th Regiment, to Reverend Dennis George Norris., Michell, John, Sir, 1781-1866 (Box 1, Folder 3a(2))
    Concerns the death of Robert Provo Norris.
    Correspondence; Norris, Dennis George, b. 1798 or 9; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
  - Manuscript copy of a letter, dated 1851 October 15, from John Craven Mansergh to Reverend Dennis George Norris., Mansergh, John Craven (Box 1, Folder 3a(3))
    Correspondence; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; Norris, Dennis George, b. 1798 or 9
  - Manuscript copy of a letter, dated 1852 January 15, from Captain Lawlor to John Michell, Lieutenant Colonel of the 6th Regiment., Lawlor, Captain (Box 1, Folder 3a(4))
    Correspondence; Michell, John, Sir, 1781-1866; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
  - Manuscripts copy of excerpts from W.R. King's Campaigning in Kaffirland., 1853? (Box 1, Folder 3a(5))
    The excerpts concern the death and burial of Robert Provo Norris.
    Correspondence; King, William Ross, 1822-1890; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
  - Manuscript copy of a letter from Morris Hall, Captain of the 6th Regiment, to Reverend Dennis George Norris., 1854 July 30; Hall, Morris, Captain (Box 1, Folder 3a(6))
    Concerns the intention to erect a tablet in memory of Robert Provo Norris.
  - Manuscript copy of excerpts of a letter from Captain Morris Hall of the Cape Mounted Rifles to an unidentified recipient., 1851 November 12; Hall, Morris, Captain (Box 1, Folder 3a(7))
    Correspondence; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
  - Newspaper clipping of an article (from an unidentified source) describing the Kaffir Bush, or Acacia Horrida., circa 1850-1852 (Box 1, Folder 3b(1))
    The native plant species served as protection for Xhosa fighters and as an obstacle to British troops during the Kaffir War.
    Clippings
  - Manuscript copy of excerpts of a letter from Captain Morris Hall to an unidentified recipient., 1851 November 12; Hall, Morris, Captain (Box 1, Folder 3b(2))
  - Letter from John Craven Mansergh, Captain of the 6th Regiment, to Dennis George Norris., 1851 November 12; Mansergh, John Craven (Box 1, Folder 3b(3))
    Written from Waterkloof, Kaffraria. Concerns the death of Robert Provo Norris.
  - Manuscript letter from John Michell to Dennis George Norris., 1851 October 15; Michell, John, Sir, 1781-1866 (Box 1, Folder 3b(4))
    Written from camp near Waterkloof. Concerns the death of Robert Provo Norris.
  - M anuscript copy of excerpts from Graham's Town Journal., 1851 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 3b(5))
    Titled "Testimony to the worth of a beloved son"; concerns the death of Robert Provo Norris.
    Newspapers; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
- Sketchbook, Series III
  - Graphite drawings and watercolor sketches of miscellaneous subjects, chiefly landscapes in South Africa., 1848?; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 sketchbook (82 leaves); 11 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Inscribed: "R.P. Norris." A piece of paper has been pasted onto the inside cover, with a note in ink reading, "Robert Provo Norris/Killed in Action 1851/ (Kaffir War)." Many of the sketches are dated 1848, which suggests that most of the content dates to this year.
    Multiple sketches appear within the volume, including watercolor landscapes and graphite portraits. Norris depicts "Simon's Town, from the North Battery" in a particularly striking graphite landscape. He sketches a map (in graphite) labeled, "Post at Line Drift," a route (the Line Drift) which he traveled frequently while stationed at Camp Peddie. Norris's sketches are carefully observed, showing military forts and the surrounding natural settings in clear and vivid detail. Included are graphite portraits of Xhosa/"Kaffir" men and women, as well as a fine graphite portrait of a "Zolah Warrior" with shield and spear held aloft and a tall feathered headpiece. There are some more melancholy sketches of local African people in Western clothes, drinking liquor and looking destitute or debauched.
    Both military and domestic architecture are shown in Norris's sketches, including parts of Cape Town, British forts, and a "Vicarage." He also features "Barnard Castle" in one highly finished drawing. Norris also tries his hand at comic sketches, perhaps imitating some of the content in his beloved "Punch" magazine, which was sent to him from his family at home in England.
    A brief set of diary entries in graphite are recorded at the end of the volume, along with a newspaper clipping about the marriage of Captain P.W.P. Wallis, the brother-in-law of Robert Provo Norris's father, Rev. D.G. Norris, to Jemima Mary Gwyne.
    Graphite drawings; South Africa -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- South Africa; Watercolors; Xhosa (African people); Sketchbooks
- Watercolors and Drawings, Series IV
  Artist's portfolio, with two interior pockets. With gilt-stamped leather label of "R.P. Norris" on front cover. Includes various notes by Norris, in graphite and in pen and ink, on interior pockets.Several graphite, watercolor, and pen and ink sketches.
  - Watercolors: landscapes and architectural subjects, ca. 1846-51; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851
    - Unidentified fort and buildings on hilltops., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 23 x 28.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(1))
      Watercolor depicts grassy hills with a set of fort-like buildings arranged on hilltops in the foreground. The scene is viewed from a distance and there are no indications of where the sketch was made. Unsigned.
      Watercolors
    - Landscape with unidentified fort at center., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor sketch.; 15 x 24.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(2))
      Watercolor sketch showing a small military fort in the middle of a grassy valley, with brushy hills surrounding it. A few figures can be seen at various points on the outskirts of the area, with one figure appearing near a small hut with a smoking chimney at right, guards stationed at points around the fort, and what seems to be a woman walking with a basket on her head at left in the foreground.
    - Landscape with fort as seen from riverbank., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor sketch; 22.5 x 28.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(3))
      Watercolor sketch showing a large stone building from a distance. In the foreground, a river or stream curves to the left. Large square rocks appear on one bank and a gnarled tree sits on the opposite bank at right. Brush covers the flats and hills surrounding the river and large blue mountains can be seen in the distance beyond the valley in which the building sits. Unsigned and unidentified.
    - "Fort Cox," brushy hills and mountains in background., circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 11 x 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(4))
      Watercolor depiction of a low stone fort with wooden gates. A British flag flies from the flagpole at center. A sentry in a red coat stands guard at right. Brushy hills and purple mountains rise in the distance. Labeled "Fort Cox" on reverse in graphite.
    - Church building in grassy valley., 1850 September 10; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 1 watercolor; 17.5 x 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(5))
      Watercolor of a Victorian style stone church with an arched Gothic glass window at front and narrow arched windows. Two figures sit on a rock in the foreground, before a small pool of water. Other buildings lie to the side of the church and an imposing blue mountain range rises in the distance. Labeled on reverse, "Sept. 10th/50."
    - Castle, "Near KW Town.", circa 1846-1851; Norris, Robert Provo, d. 1851; 2 watercolors, one on either side of sheet; 17.5 x 25.5 cm (Box 1, Folder 5a(6))
      Watercolor image of a castle seen by night. It rises on a rocky shoreline, with water seen at the right and beyond it. The viewer is situated behind the building, with some low-lying rocks in the foreground. Unlabeled.
      On the reverse is a view of grassy and bush-covered hills, with low stone buildings, sketched in graphite, seen in the distance. This image is incomplete. Labeled in graphite, "Near KW [?] Town," likely meaning that this was a view of the area near King William's Town.